Society for the Study of Gloria Anzaldúa and El Mundo Zurdo Conference Records
Nettie Lee Benson Latin American Collection
Society for the Study of Gloria Anzaldúa and El Mundo Zurdo Conference Records
2006-2020
Society for the Study of Gloria Anzaldúa
2012-07
5 linear feet
Benson Latin American Collection, The University of Texas at Austin
Collection documents El Mundo Zurdo Conference, an event organized by the Society for the Study of Gloria Anzaldúa (SSGA). The collection includes programs, video recordings, and ephemera.
Historical Note
The Society for the Study of Gloria Anzaldúa (SSGA) was founded in 2007 by Dr. Norma E. Cantú to honor the life and legacy of Gloria Evangelina Anzaldúa.
In 2007 the Güeras y Prietas symposium was organized by Norma E. Cantú, Jackie Cuevas, AnaLouise Keating, Amelia Montes, Elaine Perez, Sonia Saldívar-Hull, Glenda Schaffer, and Rita Urquijo-Ruiz.
El Mundo Zurdo conference (EMZ) is convened by the society every 18 months. Conference particiants include scholars, artists, and community members who engage with Anzaldúa's work.
Events
2007 November 03 Güeras y Prietas Symposium. University of Texas at San Antonio
2009 May 16-17 Conference. University of Texas at San Antonio
2010 November 4-6 Art and Performance. University of Texas at San Antonio
2012 May 16-19 Conference. University of Texas at San Antonio
2013 November 14-16 Activism, Philosophy, and Pedagogy. University of Texas at San Antonio
2015 May 27-30 Memoria y Conocimiento: Interdisciplinary Anzalduan Studies / Archive, Legacy, and Thought. University of Texas at Austin
2016 November 3-5 Nepantla: Theories and Practices. University of Texas at San Antonio
2018 May 17-19 10th conference. Borderlands 1987-2017: The 30th anniversary of Borderlands/La Frontera: The New Mestiza
2019 October 31-November 02 Planetary Citizenship: Anzalduan Thought Across Communities, Histories, Cultures. Trinity University (San Antonio, Texas)
2020 September 26 Tiempos Nepantla / Nepantla Times. Virtual/online event.
Scope and Contents Note
The collection is organized into four series: Administrative and Subject Files, Publications, Digital Content, and Artifacts and Memorabilia.
The Administrative and Subject Files includes early SSGA membership lists, agendas, flyers, and conference planning files. The planning files include program/schedule information, flyers, certificates of attendance, evaluation and release forms.
Publications series includes the official symposium program for Güeras y Prietas and a set of conference programs. This series also includes selected works presented at El Mundo Zurdo conferences, a book of works presented at the symposium, and a proof copy of the Borderlands/La Frontera critical edition (forthcoming summer/fall 2021).
Digital Content includes conference planning files, photographs, and El Mundo Zurdo video recordings. The series is organized by carrier format: flash drive, memory SD cards, and compact discs. The compact discs mainly include DVD-R discs and some CD-R discs.
Artifacts and Memorabilia includes candles, memory stones with Anzalduan quotes, conference bags, T-shirts, and posters.
Access Restrictions
Advance notice is required to access material from Box 5. Other material unrestricted.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Anzaldúa, Gloria
Subjects (Organizations)
Society for the Study of Gloria Anzaldúa
Subjects (Meetings)
Mundo Zurdo (Conference)
Places
Texas
Document Types
conference materials
Related Material
Gloria Evangelina Anzaldúa Papers
Records of the Memorial and Tribute to Gloria Anzaldúa
Collection on Gloria Evangelina Anzaldúa
Acquisition Information
Donation.
Accession numbers: 2012-07, 2019-36, 2021-07
Additions
Further materials are expected for this collection.
Box and Folder Inventory
- Administrative and Subject Files
  - Agendas, 2007; 2009-2010 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence (printed emails), 2007 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General files, flyers, 2007-2009 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Membership contact list, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Membership list, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Newsletter (Words from the Director), circa 2007 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - The Adelante Project consent to publish signed forms, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Planning files (Box 1)
    - Symposium/conference planning, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Güeras y Prietas symposium presenters list, papers, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Program Committee files, 2008-2009 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Conference planning (program/schedule, certificates of participation), 2008-2009 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Panel proposals, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Conference planning (flyers, clipping, release forms, evaluations, cetificates), 2010 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Conference planning, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Conference planning (schedule, evaluation form), 2013 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Conference planning (files, flyers, blank certificate), 2015 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Conference planning, art competition submissions, 2015 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Conference planning (program, evaluation forms, release forms), 2016 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Conference planning, 2018 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Includes program, evaluation forms, newsletters, postcard size flyer, and altar installation material (images, notes).
    - Conference planning (evaluations, flyer, ofrendas de palabras), 2019 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Permission to photograph/video tape/live stream forms (Box 2)
    - 2018 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - 2019 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Marathon reading of Borderlands/La Frontera (Anzaldúa reading in New York City), 2019 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Publications
  - Programs (Box 2)
    - Güeras y Prietas: Celebrating 20 years of Borderlands/La Frontera official symposium program, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Conference, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Conference, 2010 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Conference, 2012 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Conference, 2013 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Conference, 2015 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Conference, 2016 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Conference, 2018 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Conference, 2019 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - La Voz de Esperanza, San Antonio, Texas (Volume 17, Issue 6) Anzaldúa on the cover, 2004 July/August (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - GAL Project newsletter #2 (Gloria Anzaldúa Legacy Project), 2007 October (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - This Bridge We Call Home: Finding Gloria (Volume 1, second edition), 2007 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Güeras y Prietas: Celebrating 20 years of Borderlands/La Frontera edited by Norma E. Cantú and Christina L. Gutierrez, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Published by The Adelante Project.
  - El Mundo Zurdo 2: Selected works of the 2010 meeting of the Society for the Study of Gloria Anzaldúa edited by Sonia Saldívar-Hull, Norma Alarcón, and Rita E. Urquijo-Ruiz, 2012 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - El Mundo Zurdo 7: Selected works of the 2018 meeting of the Society for the Study of Gloria Anzaldúa edited by Sara A. Ramírez, Larissa M. Mercado-López, and Sonia Saldívar-Hull, 2019 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Borderlands/La Frontera Critical Edition edited by Ricardo F. Vivancos-Pérez and Norma Elia Cantú (proof copy), circa 2020 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Digital Content
  Advance notice is required to access material from Box 5.
  - El Mundo Zurdo, Society for Study of Gloria Anzaldúa (flash drive, PNY 64GB) (Box 5, Item 1)
  - Memory SD (secure digital) cards (Box 5)
    - Number 1 (SanDisk Extreme Plus, SD HC, 90 MB/32 GB) (Box 5, Item 2)
    - Number 2 (SanDisk Ultra Plus, SD HC, 48 MB/32 GB), 2016 (Box 5, Item 3)
      Envelope note indicates that card number 2 has pictures, 2016.
    - Number 3 (SanDisk Extreme, SD HC, 90 MB/16 GB) (Box 5, Item 4)
    - Number 4 (Lexar Professional, SD XC, 95 MB/64 GB) (Box 5, Item 5)
  - Compact discs (Box 5)
    Mainly DVD-R and some CD-R discs.
    - 2007-2008 (Box 5)
      - Anzaldúa Symposium Güeras y Prietas (participants, flyers, schedule, agendas, itinerary) (Box 5, Item 6)
      - Borderlands/La Frontera Poetry Readings, Trinity University (San Antonio, Texas), 2007 Novermber 02 (Box 5, Item 7)
      - Güeras y Prietas: Celebrating 20 years of Borderlands/La Frontera, Disc 1 Blessing and Welcome (2 copies), 2007 November 03 (Box 5, Item 8-9)
      - Güeras y Prietas: Celebrating 20 years of Borderlands/La Frontera, Disc 2 Session I The U.S. Mexican Border: Anzaldúa and Border Studies (Box 5, Item 10)
      - Güeras y Prietas: Celebrating 20 years of Borderlands/La Frontera, Disc 3 Session II Anzaldúa and Queer Studies (2 copies) (Box 5, Item 11-12)
      - Güeras y Prietas: Celebrating 20 years of Borderlands/La Frontera, Disc 4 Lunch Hour presentations (2 copies) (Box 5, Item 13-14)
      - Güeras y Prietas: Celebrating 20 years of Borderlands/La Frontera, Disc 5 Session III The U.S. Mexican Border: Anzaldúa y Mexico (2 copies), 2007 November 03 (Box 5, Item 15-16)
      - Güeras y Prietas: Celebrating 20 years of Borderlands/La Frontera, Disc 6 Questions and Answers from Disc 5 Session III (2 copies) (Box 5, Item 17-18)
      - Güeras y Prietas: Celebrating 20 years of Borderlands/La Frontera, Disc 7 Session IV Anzaldúa Studies: International Perspectives (2 copies) (Box 5, Item 19-20)
      - Conversations with Patsy Light and Dr. Norma Cantú, 2008 (Box 5, Item 21)
    - 2009 (Box 5)
      - Anzaldúa Conference files (Box 5, Item 22)
        Label: Registration, program, agendas, schedules, memos and letters. El Mundo Zurdo 2009.
      - The International Conference on the Life and Works of Gloria Anzaldúa Disc 1 (3 copies), 2009 May 16 (Box 5, Item 23-25)
        Opening ceremony: Dr. Norma Cantú, Dr. Sonia Saldívar-Hull. Blessing Grandma Emma Ortega. Plenary 1: Randy Conner.
      - The International Conference on the Life and Works of Gloria Anzaldúa Disc 2 Promoting Critical Thinking Among Elementary Students with Literature Authored by Gloria Anzaldúa (3 copies) (Box 5, Item 26-28)
      - The International Conference on the Life and Works of Gloria Anzaldúa - International and Transfrontera Issues (Box 5, Item 29)
      - The International Conference on the Life and Works of Gloria Anzaldúa - Closing Plenary, 2009 May 17 (Box 5, Item 30)
        Gloria Anzaldúa Composing a Life: Poesía, Teoría, Historia. Speakers include Alicia Gaspar de Alba, Antonia Castañeda, and Emma Perez.
      - The International Conference on the Life and Works of Gloria Anzaldúa - Plenary 2, 2009 May 17 (Box 5, Item 31)
        El Mundo S/Zurdo: Past Present and Future, AnaLouise Keating.
      - The International Conference on the Life and Works of Gloria Anzaldúa Photographs (Box 5, Item 32)
      - El Mundo Zurdo 2009 Exhibit and Artist Panel Photographs (Box 5, Item 33)
    - 2010-2012 (Box 5)
      - El Mundo Zurdo 2010 (program, budget, letters, moderators, flyers) (Box 5, Item 34)
      - SSGA 2011 Files for El Mundo Zurdo 2012 (Box 5, Item 35)
      - SSGA 2012 (Box 5, Item 36)
        Compact disc label: art, programs, newsletters, agendas, budget, forms, letters-thank you.
    - 2013 (Box 5)
      - El Mundo Zurdo 2013 Disc 1-8 (Box 5, Item 37-44)
- Artifacts and Memorabilia
  - Candles (Box 6)
    En español: El Retorno. El Valle celebra nuestra Gloria. English translation: The Return. The Valley celebrates our Gloria. A reference to the Rio Grande Valley region in Texas.
    Plastic containers (1 orange, 1 red) with a paper on one side that has image of Gloria Anzaldua. On the other side/back there is a quote.
    - Orange container, quote by Lauren Espinoza, undated (Box 6, Item 1)
    - Red container, quote by Erika Garza, undated (Box 6, Item 2)
  - Memory stones (Box 6)
    El Mundo Zurdo 2012, rocks have quotes from Anzalduan texts and are painted different colors.
    - Be the healing of the wound! (dark blue/navy blue), 2012 (Box 6, Item 3)
    - I change myself, I change the world (green), 2012 (Box 6, Item 4)
    - Now let us shift! (red), circa 2012 (Box 6, Item 5)
  - Conference bags (Box 7)
    - Black bag with image in color, 2009 (Box 7, Item 1)
    - Black bag with image in color, 2010 (Box 7, Item 2)
    - Black bag with image in color, 2012 (Box 7, Item 3)
    - Canvas/tan bag with purple bottom and handle (10th EMZ conference), 2018 (Box 7, Item 4)
  - T-Shirts (Box 7)
    - Red shirt, 2010 (Box 7, Item 5)
    - Blue shirt, 2012 (Box 7, Item 6)
    - Light blue with images and text in black, 2018 (Box 7, Item 7)
    - Tan color shirt, image on front of art work by Liliana Wilson, 2019 (Box 7, Item 8)
  - Conference posters, 2009; 2010,; 2012,; 2019 (Box 7, Item 9)